Guide to the Time Inc. Magazine Development Group Records 1967-1987, 2003 MS 3009-RG 40
New-York Historical Society
- Series I.A.1.b. 1973 to 1978 Editorial: Editor Philip Kunhardt Files, 1971-1978; 4.75 Linear feet in 6 record cartons
  - Subseries I.A.1.b.i. Administrative Files, 1971-1978; 0.8 Linear feet in 1 record carton
    - Expense Reports: Staff, 1974-1976 (Offsite-box 3717, Folder 12-14)
    - Kudo File on Life Special Report, 1974 (Offsite-box 3717, Folder 15)
    - Life Before Birth Letters (Reprint Requests), 1974 (Offsite-box 3717, Folder 16)
    - Life Specials, 1973 (Offsite-box 3717, Folder 17)
    - Magazine Development Meeting, 1973 May (Offsite-box 3717, Folder 18)
    - New Ideas, 1973 (Offsite-box 3717, Folder 19)
    - New Magazines: Agreement Letter, 1977-1978 (Offsite-box 3717, Folder 20)
    - Wires, 1973 (Offsite-box 3717, Folder 21)
    - Woman Magazine: Dummy #2 Complimentary Copies Sent, 1977 (Offsite-box 3717, Folder 22)
    - Woman Magazine: Memoranda, 1977 (Offsite-box 3717, Folder 23)
  - Subseries I.A.1.b.ii. Life Special Reports, 1973-1978; 3.7 Linear feet in 5 record cartons
    Historical Note
    Life Special Reports were published twice a year by former Life staff within the Magazine Development Group after the closure of the weekly Life and are a continuation of the Life special issues. LSR were sometimes called occassional Life Specials.
    Year in Pictures is the official title of the issue published in January of every year regarding the prior year. It is called colloquilly in the records the "Life Year End". 1973 is the only time the year is used in the title.
    The Spirit of Israel celebrates the 25th anniversary of the establishment of modern day Israel and events and accomplishments of the country.
    One Day in the Life of America published photographs and stories from September 5, 1974 in order to "show the essence" of the country as seen by 100 photographers.
    For the Bicentennial Issue, the MDG consulted historians to choose the events depicted in the issue and licensed photographs from museums, other historical repositories, and private collections.
    Remarkable American Women is not "a catalogue of the 'most important' women in American history. It is a gallery of individuals... we consider remarkable."
    The New Youth discusses the viewpoints and activities of American youth ages 15 through mid-20s.
    Life Special Reports contains records on the editorial decisions for these biannually published issues. Records include correspondence along with reader letters; lists of ideas; check requisitions and correspondence for payments to writers, researchers, and photographers; article drafts; photograph releases; internal memoranda; news clippings; and lists of who received complimentary copies.
    The correspondence in One Day in the Life of America includes photographers' descriptions of their rolls of film and letters from the public regarding their submissions. Additional material from One Day in the Life of America is in the Business Office General Files on Life Special Reports in a folder titled "Kunhardt file."
    Correspondence in Picture Editor John Loengard's files mention a prototype for "regular Life" that he worked on in Spring 1974. The materials in Kunhardt's protoype files might be for that although these folders were with the other LSR folders.
    Restricted materials include payments to temporary staff and stringers with personally identifiable information, and release forms from minors.
    Organized chronologically in order of publication, then alphabetically by folder title within each issue's files.
    - 1973: The Spirit of Israel (Offsite-box 3717, Folder 24-26)
    - 1973: The Spirit of Israel (Offsite-box 3718, Folder 1-2)
    - 1974: The Year in Pictures 1973, 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 3718, Folder 3-5)
    - 1974: The Year in Pictures 1973 [RESTRICTED], 1873-1874 (Offsite-box R68)
    - 1974: Prototype Issue (Offsite-box 3718, Folder 6-7)
    - 1974: One Day in the Life of America (Offsite-box 3718, Folder 8-27)
    - 1974: One Day in the Life of America (Offsite-box 3719, Folder 1-2)
    - 1974: One Day in the Life of America [RESTRICTED] (Offsite-box R68)
      May also include materials for the prototype and the Year in Pictures.
    - 1975: Year in Pictures (1974), 1974-1975 (Offsite-box 3719, Folder 3-4)
    - 1975: Bicentennial Issue: The 100 Events That Shaped America, 1975-1976 (Offsite-box 3719, Folder 5-19)
    - 1975: Bicentennial Issue: The 100 Events That Shaped America [RESTRICTED] (Offsite-box R68)
    - 1976: Year in Pictures (1975), 1975-1976 (Offsite-box 3719, Folder 20-25)
    - 1976: Year in Pictures (1975) [RESTRICTED] (Offsite-box R68)
    - 1976: Remarkable American Women (Offsite-box 3720, Folder 1-10)
    - 1976: Remarkable American Women [RESTRICTED] (Offsite-box R68)
    - 1977: Year in Pictures (1976), 1976-1977 (Offsite-box 3720, Folder 11-12)
    - 1977: Year in Pictures (1976) [RESTRICTED] (Offsite-box R68)
    - 1977: The New Youth (Offsite-box 3720, Folder 13-18)
    - 1977: The New Youth [RESTRICTED] (Offsite-box R68)
    - 1978: Year in Pictures (1977), 1977-1978 (Offsite-box 3720, Folder 19-22)
    - 1978: Year in Pictures (1977) [RESTRICTED] (Offsite-box R68)
  - Subseries I.A.1.b.iii. People Test Issue Files, 1973; 0.25 Linear feet in 2 record cartons
    The records document editorial work on People magazine dummies and test issues prior to its first publication in 1974. Records include lists of magazine sections and article topics; correspondence and cables; check requisitions to pay photographers and photo agencies; expense reports from MDG staff and from the News Service for use of stringers; and notepads listing photograph credits.
    The General folders include a call for story submissions sent to all the Time Inc. domestic and foreign news bureaus and an exchange between Kunhardt and former Life correspondent and bureau chief Dora Jane Hamblin regarding their blunt opinions of the new magazine. In his letter to Hamblin, Kunhardt states he will no longer be working on People.
    Restricted material includes payroll records with personally identifiable information.
    Organized alphabetically.
    - General, 1973 (Offsite-box 3721, Folder 1-2)
    - Payments and Complimentary Copies, 1973 (Offsite-box 3721, Folder 3)
    - Payments and Memoranda, 1973 (Offsite-box 3721, Folder 4)
    - Payments and Memoranda [RESTRICTED], 1973 (Offsite-box R68)
    - Payments to Staff, 1973 (Offsite-box 3721, Folder 5)
    - Payments to Staff [RESTRICTED], 1973 (Offsite-box R68)
    - Test Issue [RESTRICTED], 1973 (Offsite-box R68)
- Series I.A.2. 1973 to 1978 Editorial: Acting Editor Kelso Sutton Files, 1973-1976; 0.5 Linear feet in 1 record carton
  Kelso Sutton's files document his tenure as Acting Editor of the Magazine Development Group while Kunhardt was on sabbatical. He was also Vice President of Magazines at this time.
  - Home Box Office (HBO), 1976 (Offsite-box 3721, Folder 6)
  - Magazine Development: Memoranda, 1976 (Offsite-box 3721, Folder 7)
  - Magazine Development: Overtime Statement, 1976 (Offsite-box 3721, Folder 8)
  - Magazine Development: Weekly Reports, 1976 (Offsite-box 3721, Folder 9)
  - Magazine Ideas for Time Inc., 1976 (Offsite-box 3721, Folder 10)
  - Memoranda on New Magazines, 1976 (Offsite-box 3721, Folder 11)
  - Money: Memoranda, 1976 (Offsite-box 3721, Folder 12)
  - People: Memoranda, 1976 (Offsite-box 3721, Folder 13-14)
  - Television and Cable, 1973-1976 (Offsite-box 3721, Folder 15)
  - Time Inc.: General, 1976 (Offsite-box 3721, Folder 16)
  - Time Inc.: Staff Memoranda, 1976 (Offsite-box 3721, Folder 17)
  - Women's Magazine Memoranda and Research, 1976 (Offsite-box 3721, Folder 18-19)
- Series I.A.3. 1973 to 1978 Editorial: Office of the Editor General Correspondence, 1974-1976; 0.2 Linear feet in 1 record carton
  This correspondence comes from the head of editorial of the Magazine Development Group, primarily while Philip Kunhardt held the position. It includes correspondence to and from editors Otto Fuerbringer, Kunhardt, and Kelso Sutton; Picture Editor John Loengard, and secretary to Fuerbringer and Kunhardt Ann Morrell. Topics include suggestions for new magazines; Life Special Reports (LSR) theme and article suggestions from staff and from outside Time Inc.; questions about the future of Life magazine; infomation on photographs in Life and LSR; and replies to unsolicited photograph submissions.
  Includes a folder titled "Leadbelly Screening" regarding photojournalist, film director, and Life contributor Gordon Parks's invitation to Time Inc. staff to early screenings of his motion picture Leadbelly.
  Organized alphabetically based on the original arrangement.
  - Correspondence: A-Z, 1974-1976 (Offsite-box 3721, Folder 20-47)
- Series I.A.4. 1973 to 1978 Editorial: Women's Magazine Editor Patricia Ryan Files, 1976-1977; 0.1 Linear feet in 2 folders
  While she would later become the first woman managing editor at Time Inc. in 1982 (of People), Patricia Ryan's files indicate she was on loan from Sports Illustrated to develop the women's magazine. Records in Paul Hale's files indicate the women's magazine editorial department was overseen by Otto Fuerbringer with assistance from Ryan.
  According to materials in Philip Kunhardt's files, a dummy was created in mid-1977 and circulated to select women at Time Inc. for comment. A September 1976 memorandum from Philip Kunhardt to Stephen LaRue in LaRue's files states that the magazine must be "put together by women."
  These two folders were found with Kunhardt's files, but have no indication they were given to him by Patricia Ryan.
  Ryan's files on the women's magazine under development by the Magazine Development Group include requests for and responses to submitted articles and lists of Time Inc. staff who should receive a test copy for review.
  The majority of records documenting the history of the work on this publication are in Stephen LaRue's, Paul Hale's, and Mary Davis's files.
  - Assignments, 1976-1977 (Offsite-box 3721, Folder 48)
  - Complimentary Copy List, 1977 (Offsite-box 3721, Folder 49)
- Series I.A.5. 1973 to 1978 Editorial: Life Special Reports Picture Editor John Loengard Files, 1974; 0.1 Linear feet in 3 folders
  John Loengard was a picture editor for Life when it closed in 1972 and transferred to the Magazine Development Group (MDG) like many of the former Life staff. In 1974 he was the Picture Editor for the Life Special Reports within the MDG.
  Records include correspondence to and from freelance photographers and the public regarding submissions for One Day in the Life of America and requests for images to publish in the Year in Pictures (1974), particularly of Nixon.
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Offsite-box 3722, Folder 1-2)
  - Photo Lab Orders, 1974 (Offsite-box 3722, Folder 3)
- Series I.B.1. 1973 to 1978 Business and Publishing: Archives Transfer Forms, 1976-1978; 0.1 Linear feet in 1 folder
  This folder includes all transfer forms collected by the archivist that were found with boxes of material related to the business and publishing staff for the first Magazine Development Group. Because People was developed by the MDG, some material shows originating with the People Business Office. Forms did not always match up with the surrounding material in the box, and, in some cases, the material described on the form is not present in the collection.
  Series is one folder.
  - Transfer Forms, 1976-1978 (Offsite-box 3722, Folder 4)
- Series I.B.2. 1973 to 1978 Business and Publishing: Director and Publisher Garry Valk Slides, 1975; 0.1 Linear feet in 1 record carton
  The only item in Director and Publisher Garry Valk's files is the slide carousel for a presentation to the Time Inc. Board of Directions on the results of a Future of Magazines study conducted by the Magazine Development Group on behalf of the operating group for magazines. No other files for Valk have been located although correspondence and memoranda from him are interspersed throughout others' records in this record group.
  A January 1984 memorandum from Bruce Barnet (in his files outside of this record group) states that Valk's files were discarded once he left Time Inc.
  Series is a single item.
  - Future of Magazines, 1975 (Offsite-box 3722, Item 1)
- Series I.B.3. 1973 to 1978 Business and Publishing: Associate Director Stephen LaRue Files, 1976-1978; 4 Linear feet in 4 record cartons
  Stephen LaRue joined the Magazine Development Group in mid-1976 after leaving his position as President of Time Canada. After the closure of the MDG, he was assigned as Assistant Publisher of Time.
  Stephen LaRue's files document the publishing decisions of the first Magazine Development Group regarding new ideas submitted and the women's magazine.
  Organized into two subseries:
  Subseries I.B.3.a. New Ideas
  Subseries I.B.3.b. Women's Magazine
  Subseries are based on the original groupings of files.
  - Subseries I.B.3.a. New Ideas, 1976-1978; 0.75 Linear feet in 1 record carton
    New Ideas contains correspondence and memoranda regarding proposals for new magazine ideas from people and companies outside of Time Inc. A note in the "Prime Time" folder indicates most of the material was forwarded to Garry Valk and Deane Raley. The remaining materials discuss a television oriented publication to be "an upscale competitor to TV Guide." Perhaps this idea was a precursor to TV-Cable Week.
    Organized alphabetically by the name of the correspondent or proposed magazine based on the original folder title.
    - General, 1977-1978 (Offsite-box 3739, Folder 1-4)
    - Allan Grant Productions, 1977 (Offsite-box 3739, Folder 5)
    - "The American Road" / Roger Vaughan, 1976-1977 (Offsite-box 3739, Folder 6)
    - Brown, Bob / Allen, Frank, 1977 (Offsite-box 3739, Folder 7)
    - "Enjoy" / The Catalyst Corporation, 1977 (Offsite-box 3739, Folder 8)
    - Finch, Rufus C., Jr. / Metaphysical magazine, 1977 (Offsite-box 3739, Folder 9)
    - Kucharsky, David / Religion magazine, 1977 (Offsite-box 3739, Folder 10)
    - "Movie Guide Magazine" / Crossover Communications, 1977 (Offsite-box 3739, Folder 11)
    - "New York World Times" / S. Stillman, 1977 (Offsite-box 3739, Folder 12)
    - Pillow Talk, 1977 (Offsite-box 3739, Folder 13)
    - Popcorn, Inc., 1977 (Offsite-box 3739, Folder 14)
    - "Prime Time", 1977 (Offsite-box 3739, Folder 15)
  - Subseries I.B.3.b. Women's Magazine, 1976-1978; 3.25 Linear feet in 4 record cartons
    LaRue, along with Paul Hale and Mary Davis, has the majority of records on the women's magazine including extensive files on the creation and testing of the two dummy issues and a collection of other magazines intended for women as research. A September 1976 memorandum from Philip Kunhardt to LaRue states that the magazine must be "put together by women." According to materials in Philip Kunhardt's files, a dummy was created in mid-1977 and circulated to select women at Time Inc. for comment.
    While Woman is the working title the Magazine Development Group wanted to use, records also refer to the project as the woman's magazine, the women's magazine, Project "X" or "W". The business side did a lot of work starting mid-1976 in order to begin creating dummies, trademark research, costs, and possible revenues. The "General" file includes a prospectus on "Magazine X" and the "Printed Dummy" files list stores used for market testing.
    - General, 1976-1977 (Offsite-box 3739, Folder 16-18)
    - Ads for Women's Magazines, 1977 (Offsite-box 3739, Folder 19-21)
    - Advertising: Space Commitments, 1977 (Offsite-box 3740, Folder 1)
    - Concepts, 1977 (Offsite-box 3740, Folder 2-3)
    - Cost Analyses, 1977 (Offsite-box 3740, Folder 4-6)
    - Market Research, 1977 (Offsite-box 3740, Folder 7-9)
    - Market Testing, 1977-1978 (Offsite-box 3740, Folder 10-12)
    - Personnel, 1977 (Offsite-box 3740, Folder 13-14)
    - Other Magazines: Positioning, 1976 (Offsite-box 3740, Folder 15-16)
    - Printed Dummy #1: Ads, 1977 (Offsite-box 3740, Folder 17-18)
    - Printed Dummy #1: Distribution, 1977 (Offsite-box 3741, Folder 1-2)
    - Printed Dummy #1: Market Research, 1977 (Offsite-box 3741, Folder 3-6)
    - Printed Dummy #1: Opinions, 1977 (Offsite-box 3741, Folder 7)
    - Printed Dummy #1: Production Costs, 1976-1977 (Offsite-box 3741, Folder 8)
    - Printed Dummy #2: Advertisers, 1977 (Offsite-box 3741, Folder 9)
    - Printed Dummy #2: Distribution, 1977 (Offsite-box 3741, Folder 10-11)
    - Printed Dummy #2: Market Research, 1977 (Offsite-box 3741, Folder 12-13)
    - Printed Dummy #2: Opinions, 1977 (Offsite-box 3741, Folder 14-15)
    - Printed Dummy #2: Profits and Losses, 1977 (Offsite-box 3741, Folder 16)
    - Printed Dummy #2: Production Costs and Schedules, 1977 (Offsite-box 3742, Folder 1)
    - Printed Dummy #2: Test Plan, 1977 (Offsite-box 3742, Folder 2)
    - Promotion and Publicity, 1977 (Offsite-box 3742, Folder 3-4)
    - Prototype: Qualitative Study, 1977 (Offsite-box 3742, Folder 5)
    - Small-sized Dummy Description, 1977 (Offsite-box 3742, Folder 6)
    - Staff Opinions, 1977 (Offsite-box 3742, Folder 7)
    - Sterling Forest Meeting, 1976 (Offsite-box 3742, Folder 8)
    - Subscriptions to Outside Magazines, 1977 (Offsite-box 3742, Folder 9-12)
    - Trademark / Legal, 1977-1978 (Offsite-box 3742, Folder 13-15)
    - Zalduondo, Lucille de, 1976 (Offsite-box 3742, Folder 16)
- Series I.B.4.a. 1973 to 1978 Business and Publishing: General Manager Winston Cox Files, 1971-1975; 3,25 Linear feet in 4 record cartons
  Winston "Tony" Cox was the Life Business Manager when it closed in 1972. He was an original member of the new Magazine Development Group as the General Manager (GM). By 1976 Deane Raley took over as GM, and Cox moved on to corporate administration at the Home Box Office (HBO).
  Winston Cox's files document the business decisions of the early Magazine Development Group, particularly its work finding advertisers, studies on circulation, and budget forecasting. His files also contain the majority of work done on the Future of Magazines study and presentation.
  Subsubseries I.B.3.a. Administrative Files
  Subsubseries I.B.3.b. Future of Magazines Study
  Subsubseries I.B.3.c. Magazines
  - Subseries I.B.4.a.i. Administrative Files, 1972-1974; 0.75 Linear feet in 1 record carton
    Winston Cox's administrative files include general records from the business side of the Magazine Development Group.
    - Accounting, 1974 (Offsite-box 3722, Folder 5a)
    - Bicentennial / America Proposal, 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 3722, Folder 5b)
    - Budget: General, 1974 (Offsite-box 3722, Folder 6)
    - Budget: Divisional, 1973 (Offsite-box 3722, Folder 7)
    - C. F. Boone (Publisher), 1973? (Offsite-box 3722, Folder 8-9)
    - Creative Services Agreement, 1974 (Offsite-box 3722, Folder 10)
    - Direct Mail, 1974-1975 (Offsite-box 3722, Folder 11-12)
    - Ideas: Children's Magazine, 1972-1973 (Offsite-box 3722, Folder 13)
    - Marketing, 1974 (Offsite-box 3722, Folder 14)
    - Pre-Spending, 1973 (Offsite-box 3722, Folder 15)
    - Public Relations Budget, 1974 (Offsite-box 3722, Folder 16)
    - Raise Review, 1974 (Offsite-box 3722, Folder 17)
    - Reconciliations, 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 3722, Folder 18-19)
    - Reestimates, 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 3722, Folder 20)
    - Special Rate Memorandum, 1974 (Offsite-box 3722, Folder 21)
    - Staff Expenses, 1973 (Offsite-box 3722, Folder 22)
    - Strategic Planning: 18-Month Forecast, 1974 (Offsite-box 3722, Folder 23)
    - Strategic Planning: One-Year Forecast, 1974 (Offsite-box 3722, Folder 24)
    - Strategic Planning: Three-Year Plan, 1973 (Offsite-box 3722, Folder 25)
  - Subseries I.B.4.a.ii. Future of Magazines Study, 1971-1975; 1.2 Linear feet in 2 record cartons
    According to a memorandum from Cox to Murray Gart in July 1975, Time Inc. requested that the operating groups for Books and Magazines prepare a study on the future of their area for the Board of Directors. The Magazines group tasked the Magazine Development Group with the study on the future of magazines for presentation to the Board in August 1975.
    Winston Cox's files on the study of the future of magazines identify trends that occurred in the magazine business in the years prior to the study and attempt to identify trends that will affect magazines in the future in order, and compare general magazine trends to Time Inc. magazine trends. Records include reports on the performance of "quality" magazines, interests and actions of advertisers particularly focusing on tobacco, alcohol and automotive, reports and studies on consumers collected from other companies and professional organizations, charts of trends in revenue and costs, and materials used in the presentation to the Board of Directors.
    - General, 1974-1975 (Offsite-box 3723, Folder 1-4)
    - Advertiser Costs, circa 1974 (Offsite-box 3723, Folder 5)
    - Advertiser Demand, 1971-1975 (Offsite-box 3723, Folder 6)
    - Breseman Charts, 1975? (Offsite-box 3723, Folder 7-8)
    - Conclusions, 1975 (Offsite-box 3723, Folder 9)
    - Economy and Consumers, 1972-1975 (Offsite-box 3723, Folder 10-12)
    - Magazine Study, 1975 (Offsite-box 3723, Folder 13-14)
    - Outline, 1975 (Offsite-box 3723, Folder 15)
    - Physical Costs, 1973-1975 (Offsite-box 3723, Folder 16)
    - Presentation: Originals, 1975? (Offsite-box 3723, Folder 17-19)
    - Reader Costs, 1974 (Offsite-box 3723, Folder 20)
    - Reader Demand, 1974-1975 (Offsite-box 3723, Folder 21)
    - Report, 1975? (Offsite-box 3723, Folder 22)
    - Report, 1975? (Offsite-box 3724, Folder 1-2)
    - Time Inc. Magazines, 1975 (Offsite-box 3724, Folder 3-4)
    - To Do, 1975 (Offsite-box 3724, Folder 5)
  - Subseries I.B.4.a.iii. Magazines, 1971-1975
    Winston Cox's files on magazines under development document the business side's preparation for the launch of People and work during its first year of publication. The records focus on advertising and circulation. These files also include possible prototypes or test issues for View, and circulation reports on Well and Money that originated with George Wiedemann, part of Corporate Circulation.
    - People: Advertising, 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 3724, Folder 6)
    - People: Advertising: Ad Bonus Plan, 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 3724, Folder 7)
    - People: Advertising: Circulation Trade Adversiting, 1973 (Offsite-box 3724, Folder 8)
    - People: Advertising: Cover Positions, 1974 (Offsite-box 3724, Folder 9)
    - People: Advertising: Edt Mockups by Issue, 1974 (Offsite-box 3724, Folder 10)
    - People: Advertising: House Ads, 1974 (Offsite-box 3724, Folder 11)
    - People: Advertising: Insert Cards, 1974 (Offsite-box 3724, Folder 12-13)
    - People: Advertising: Introductory Discount, 1974? (Offsite-box 3724, Folder 14)
    - People: Advertising: Monthly Advertising Report, 1974 (Offsite-box 3724, Folder 15)
    - People: Advertising: New Business, 1974 (Offsite-box 3724, Folder 16)
    - People: Advertising: Paid Avertising for PIB Reports, 1974 (Offsite-box 3724, Folder 17)
    - People: Advertising: Policy, 1974 (Offsite-box 3724, Folder 18)
    - People: Advertising: Promotion, 1974 (Offsite-box 3724, Folder 19)
    - People: Advertising: Public Services in People or Money, 1973 (Offsite-box 3724, Folder 20)
    - People: Advertising: Rates, 1974 (Offsite-box 3724, Folder 21)
    - People: Advertising: Rebates, 1972-1975 (Offsite-box 3724, Folder 22)
    - People: Advertising: Records, 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 3724, Folder 23)
    - People: Advertising: Report By Issue, 1974 (Offsite-box 3724, Folder 24)
    - People: Advertising: Reporting and Billing Systems, 1973 (Offsite-box 3724, Folder 25)
    - People: Advertising: Research, 1974 (Offsite-box 3724, Folder 26)